原作者名：Everyday Astronaut
视频来源：youtu.be/P-yWHOgi6so
原视频发布日期：20190105
翻译：Severus Skywalker
校对：旋火
嗨 是我 Tim Dodd 每日宇航员
Hi it's me, Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut.
没有什么比超棒的火箭想法更让人兴奋的了
There's nothing more exciting than a awesome rocket concept,
去往未知世界的新任务 或者是激动人心的技术突破
a new mission to unknown worlds, or an exciting breakthrough in technology.
但不幸地是 每一个被选择的方案都代表着有方案被砍
But unfortunately for every proposal there's almost an equal amount of cancellations
只有一小部分能离开图纸 得到实现
with only a small handful making it beyond the drawing board.
更令人沮丧的是 当这些概念真正离开了图纸
What's even more frustrating is when these concepts actually leave paper.
成千上万的工程时间投入
And thousands of engineering hours put in,
零件已经开始建造 投入了数百万美元 然后就被束之高阁了
hardware even gets built, billions of dollars invested and then it gets put on the shelf.
如果你觉得这听起来很熟悉 欢迎来到我的 取消 系列的第二集
If this sounds familiar to you, welcome to part two of my new canceled series.
我们要看看一些太空计划和概念 它们是如此接近完成
We're gonna take a look at some space programs and concepts that were so close to complete.
有时甚至在被取消之前已经发射过了
They sometimes were even launched before it got canceled.
哦 伙计 这些视频是非常令人沮丧的
Oh man, these videos are pretty frustrating.
记着这一条 那么我们开始吧
So with that in mind, let's get started.
3 2 1
所有发动机正常
All engine running.
起飞正常
Liftoff. We have a liftoff.
欢迎来到 取消 的第二集 同样
Welcome to part two of canceled, where again,
我们关注的是一些在它消失之前真正飞起来的东西
we're focusing on hardware that actually flew before it fizzled,
建成后就拜拜了 完工后就取消了
it was built and then bye bye, completed then canned.
你懂的
You get the idea.
截止20200820还没出新的
这个系列还会有更多的视频 敬请关注
There's gonna be a lot more videos coming up in this series, so stay tuned.
苏联月球着陆器
还记得美国和苏联之间所谓的太空竞赛？
Remember the so called space race between the United States and the Soviet Union?
尽管美国将登陆月球作为最终目标 并因此获得优势
Despite the US literally moving the goalpost by setting landing on the moon as the end goal,
苏联在其他几乎所有的太空里程碑上都明显地击败了美国
the Soviet Union was clearly beating the United States in almost every other space milestone.
所以 随着月球成为两国的新目标
So with the moon now the new target for both countries,
必须设计出最宏伟专业的航天器
the most ambitious and specialized spacecraft had to be designed.
因此 每个国家不仅需要制造具有足够能力的大型火箭
So not only did each country build massive, massive rockets with enough capability
将航天器真正送上月球
to actually get a spacecraft out to the moon,
但他们还必须建造能够登陆月球并回家的航天器
but they also had to build vehicles which could land on the moon and come home.
当然 美国建造了标志性的阿波罗登月舱 她搭载在土星五号火箭之上
Of course the United States built the iconic Apollo Lunar Module which rode on top of the Saturn V rocket.
但你知道吗？
But did you know,
苏联设计并建造了LK或月球飞船 来搭载在他们的N-1火箭之上
the Soviet Union designed and built the LK or Lunar Craft to ride on top of their N-1 rocket?
没错
That's right.
当全世界都在看着美国测试和飞行他们的阿波罗飞船的时候
While the world watched as the United States tested and flew their Apollo spacecraft,
苏联自个正在偷摸着研究一个非常小的月球登陆器
the Soviet Union was secretly working on a very small lunar lander themselves.
LK非常小
The LK was tiny.
只有阿波罗登月舱的三分之一大小
Only about one third the size of the Apollo Lunar Module
而且只能携带一名宇航员 而不是像阿波罗登陆器那样可以携带两名宇航员
and could only carry one cosmonaut as opposed to two like the Apollo Lander could.
你能想象吗？
Can you imagine?
只有一个人在月球上行走？
Just a single person walking around on the moon?
独自一人 完全与世隔绝
All alone, completely isolated.
这听起来绝对是可怕的
That sounds absolutely terrifying.
关于LK的一些有趣的事实
A few fun facts about the LK.
首先 LK和联盟7K -L3 LK飞船之间没有通道
First off, there was no tunnel between the LK and the Soyuz 7K-L3 LK spacecraft,
所以宇航员要做一次太空行走才能进入LK内部
so the cosmonaut was going to have to do a space walk to get inside the LK.
苏联人在实际登陆月球时 也有一个非常不同的方法
The soviets also had a much different approach to actually landing on the moon.
他们首先会派出一个无人驾驶的月球步行者探测器来选择一个合适的着陆区域
They would first send send an uncrewed Lunokhod probe to select a suitable landing area.
*并非按照比例绘制*
然后它将作为一个信标来确保LK的精确着陆
It would then act as a beacon to ensure a precise landing for the LK.
另一个有趣的事实是 他们其实每次任务都会向月球发送两个LK
Another interesting fact is they would have actually sent two LKs to the moon for each mission.
一艘提前发射 作为备用 以防有人驾驶的着陆器出现任何问题
One ahead of time, uncrewed as a backup if there were any issues with the crewed lander.
这是不是确保宇航员离开月球的唯一后备
And this wasn't the only backup to ensure their cosmonauts got off the moon, no,
在LK上 苏联人都留有冗余
the soviets were all about redundancy with the LK.
LK实际上有主引擎和备用引擎 以确保他们能把宇航员送出月球
The LK actually had primary and backup engines to ensure they could get their cosmonaut off the moon.
相比之下 阿波罗月球登陆器只有一个引擎来离开月球
Now by contrast, the Apollo Lunar lander only had only one engine to get off the moon.
最疯狂的是 这个引擎只能启动一次
The crazy thing is this engine could only be started once ever,
所以 在每次任务中使用的发动机 在发射之前甚至不能测试(试车)
so the actual engines used in the missions couldn't even be tested before they fired.
这对我来说简直是疯了
And that to me is just crazy.
所以这些引擎唯一一次发射是为了让宇航员离开月球
So the one and only time these engines fired was to get astronauts off the moon.
如果它不工作 他们就在月球上等死吧
If it didn't work, they were stuck.
最后 LK只有一个分级负责着陆和上升
And lastly, the LK only used a single stage to land on and ascend from the moon.
但它在上升时确实抛弃了起落架和其他结构 以减轻重量
But It did ditch the landing gear and other structure to decrease weight for ascent.
但这又与阿波罗着陆器有单独的下降和上升级形成了相当大的反差
But this again is in quite big contrast to the Apollo lander which had a separate descent and ascent stage.
说了这么多
All said and done,
苏联人做足了功课 有了一个非常棒的小飞船来安全登陆月球
the Soviets had done their homework and had a pretty great little spacecraft to safely land on the moon.
但最疯狂的是 他们在1970年到1971年之间 居然打了4个上去
But here's the craziest thing, they actually flew 4 of them into space between 1970 and 1971,
虽然没有一艘飞到了月球
although they never took one to the moon.
这主要是因为他们登月用的大火箭
This is mostly because their moon rocket,
N-1的4次发射 都炸了
the N-1, had 4 launch attempts, all ending in massive explosions.
由于没有合适的运载工具进入太空 LK号从未离开近地轨道
With no suitable ride to space, the LK never made it beyond Low Earth Orbit.
随着美国成功将人类送上月球
With the United States successfully putting humans on the moon,
登月的动机和资金很快就枯竭了
the motivations and funding pretty quickly dried up.
这还不算 他们还失去了一个N1的发射台
And that's not to mention they lost one of their N1 launch pads
以及他们的首席工程师谢尔盖·科罗廖夫在项目开发期间去世了
as well as their lead engineer Sergei Korolev during the development of the program,
所以他们在1974年就把整个项目砍了
so they pulled the plug on the entire program in 1974.
真可惜
What a shame.
我真的很喜欢这种登陆月球的独特方式
I really love this unique approach to landing on the moon.
但你能想象 你是唯一一个完全独自站在月球上的人吗？
But again, can you imagine being the only person standing on the moon completely alone?
想到这里 我就不寒而栗
It gives me shivers just thinking about it.
那一定会很紧张
That would have been intense.
今天你可以在莫斯科航空学院看到剩下的五架LK中的一架
Today you can see one of the five remaining LK's at the Moscow Aviaition Institute,
在奥雷沃研究和教育设施
the Orevo Research and Educational Facility,
位于科罗廖夫 坦波夫空军基地的RKK Energia工厂
the RKK Energia Plant at Korolev, Tambov Air Base,
或圣彼得堡的军事航天学院
or the Military Space Academy in St. Petersberg.
这个视频好像鸽子了，截止20200820没看到
我们将在即将到来的关于另一个航天历史的视频中 谈论更多关于N-1火箭的内容
We'll talk more about the N-1 rocket in an upcoming video about alternate space history
因为N -1没搞出来
since the N-1 never quite made it out of development.
我的意思是它肯定飞了 只是不成功
I mean sure it flew, just not successfully.
德尔塔-3
（轻流行音乐）
(light pop music)
德尔塔火箭
The Delta rocket.
也许你对最近退役的美丽的火箭 德尔塔2很熟悉
Maybe you're familiar with the recently retired and beautiful teel rocket, the Delta II,
或者说是目前飞行的最橙的火箭
or perhaps the orangest rocket currently flying,
德尔塔4和德尔塔4重型
the Delta IV and Delta IV Heavy.
或者你是个历史爱好者 还记得雷神德尔塔或德尔塔一号那些变种
Or maybe you're a history buff and remember the Thor-Delta or Delta I variants.
很多德尔塔 但德尔塔3呢？
Lots of Deltas, but what about the Delta III?
为什么我们听到这么多关于德尔塔2和德尔塔4的消息？
Why do we hear so much about II and IV?
德尔塔3在哪里？
Where's Delta III?
好吧 其实有一个德尔塔3 并且够讽刺的是
Well, there actually was a Delta III and ironically enough,
它几乎完全介于德尔塔2和德尔塔4之间
it's almost exactly between a Delta II and a Delta IV.
如果你问我的话 我觉得它看起来非常怪
A very strange looking vehicle if you ask me.
90年代中期由麦克唐纳道格拉斯公司研制
Developed in the mid 90's by McDonnell Douglas,
并在两家公司合并后由波音公司发射
and later launched by Boeing after a merger of the two companies,
德尔塔3基本上是放大的德尔塔2
the Delta III was basically a scaled up Delta II.
它使用同样的RS-27A主引擎和两个游标引擎进行滚转控制
It used that same RS-27A main engine and two vernier engines for roll control,
但这里有一个奇怪的事情
but here's the weird thing.
它与德尔塔2用同样的2.4米直径的芯级
It shared the same 2.4 meter diameter core as the Delta II,
但它里面只有液氧
but it only had the liquid oxygen in there,
然后它渐渐变大到4米 用于RP-1燃料箱
and then it tapered up to four meters for the RP-1 tank.
RS-27A的主发动机太弱了 实际上无法推动这枚更大的火箭
The RS-27A main engine was too weak to actually lift this bigger rocket,
所以德尔塔3总是需要9个大型的GEM LDXL固体火箭助推器才能把它发射出去
so the Delta III would always require nine large GEM LDXL Solid Rocket Boosters just to get it off the pad.
德尔塔3使用了一种新的末级 叫做德尔塔低温第二级
The Delta III used a new upperstage called the Delta Cryogenic Second Stage
它使用液氢和液氧来驱动RL-10B-2发动机
which used liquid Hydrogen and Oxygen to power an RL-10B-2 engine.
这台发动机很特别
This engine was pretty special
因为它提供了一个独特的延伸喷嘴
because it offered a unique extending nozzle
在保持紧凑设计的同时 提供了更高的效率
which offered increased efficiency while maintaining a compact design.
这种上级提供了更好的性能
This upperstage offered much better performance
与使用自燃推进剂的德尔塔2火箭的德尔塔K上级相比
when compared to the Delta-K upperstage of the Delta II which used hypergolic propellants.
说了这么多
All said and done,
相比德尔塔2 德尔塔3 在地静止转移轨道能够有双倍的有效载荷
the Delta III was capable of taking double the payload to Geostationary Transfer Orbit compared to the Delta II.
这是令人印象深刻的
That's impressive.
德尔塔3号于1999年8月26日从佛罗里达州的卡纳维拉尔角空军基地首次发射
The Delta III first launched on August 26th, 1999 from Cape Canaveral Air Force Station in Florida.
由于使用德尔塔2控制系统时没有进行足够的验证 导致软件错误
A software error caused by using the Delta II guidance systems without enough validations
导致火箭完全失败
caused a complete failure of the rocket
此时 火箭用于转向的液压液体用完了
when the vehicle ran out of hydraulic fluid used to steer the vehicle.
它在飞行中被毁
It was destroyed in flight.
下一次在1999年5月的发射也失败了 因为上面级发动机在第二次点火时裂开了
The next flight in May 1999 failed when the upperstage engine cracked open during its second burn.
这对于非常可靠的发动机的RL-10来说是不寻常的
This is unusual for the RL-10 which is typically a very reliable engine.
对波音公司和德尔塔3来说 这只是运气不好
It was just bad luck for the Boeing and the Delta III.
最后一次飞行发生在2000年8月23日
The final flight took place on August 23, 2000.
它进行得还不错 但不幸地是表现不佳
It went okay, but unfortunately underperformed,
使有效载荷的轨道低于目标轨道
leaving the dummy payload in a lower than targeted orbit.
所以尽管在允许误差范围内发射成功 但已经为时已晚
So despite being within the allowable margin of error for success, it was already too late.
随着德尔塔4的推出 以及前三次发射的糟糕表现
With the Delta IV coming online and the poor performance of the first three launches,
德尔塔3被取消 而波音则专注于德尔塔4
Delta III was scrapped to focus on the Delta IV.
虽然她不会有机会被人们很好的记住和喜爱
Although it wouldn't get a chance to be well remembered or loved,
她确实执行了重要的工作 验证了后来成为德尔塔4的上面级
it did perform the important work of verifying what would become the Delta IV's upperstage.
所以 至少她在其短暂的寿命中成功地完成了一些工作
So at least it did something successfully in its short lifespan.
现在 如果你开车在加州转转
Today if you're ever driving around in California,
你可能会看到德尔塔3最后剩下的一个部件
you may actually see one of the last remaining bits of a Delta III
它处在加州圣安娜的5号州际公路上
if you're driving on Interstate 5 in Santa Ana, California.
上面级就挂在发现科学中心的外面
There's the upperstage just hanging out outside of the Discovery Science Center,
甚至是包括延伸喷嘴RL-10b-2的完整版上面级
complete with the extending nozzle RL-10b-2 even.
TKS飞船
（轻流行音乐）
(light pop music)
你有没有注意到 俄罗斯喜欢那种看起来跟个球似的太空飞船？
Have you ever noticed that Russia loves spacecrafts that sort of look like a shiny ball?
至少他们的联盟号和我们最熟悉的东方号就超圆的
At least their Soyuz and Vostok that we're most familiar with are strangely super round.
在我看来 联盟号的返回舱看起来更像是一颗美味的橡皮糖 而不是飞船
In my opinion, the Soyuz descent module looks like more like a delicious gumdrop than a spacecraft.
这些与截然不同的圆锥体形状相当不同
These are pretty different from the truncated cone shapes,
而圆锥形状在西方的航天器往往是更标准的设计
like what tends been more standard in the western hemisphere.
如水星 双子座 阿波罗 龙
Such as Mercury, Gemini, Apollo, Dragon,
星际客机 猎户座 等等
Starliner, Orion, et cetera, et cetera.
但你知道苏联实际上做过看起来一点也不像联盟号的飞船
But did you know the Soviet Union actually made their own capsule that looks nothing like the Soyuz.
说了半天我的意思是 她甚至可以偷偷溜进NASA的大门
I mean so much so, it maybe could've slipped through the doors of NASA unnoticed?
来看看VA飞船
Welcome the VA spacecraft.
如果阿波罗一天晚上喝醉了爬上了联盟号的床 生下来一个小孩
If the Apollo Soyuz test project made a baby,
那么这个小孩就是VA 而且能在他身上找到阿波罗的基因
the Apollo capsule's genes clearly won out here with the VA.
但这还不是全部 他们不仅制造了VA 还有一个叫FGB舱的大型货物功能舱
But that's not all, they made the VA and there was a Large Functional Cargo Block called the FGB module.
这俩共同组成了TKS飞船
And together they formed the TKS spacecraft.
这个东西相当大
This thing was quite big.
长13.2米 宽4.15米
At 13.2 meters long and 4.15 meters wide,
TKS甚至比阿波罗指令舱和服务舱还要大
the TKS was even larger than the Apollo Command and Service Module
内部容积疯狂地达到了对方的7.5倍
and offered a crazy 7.5 times the internal volume.
TKS几乎是一个迷你空间站
The TKS was almost a mini space station.
但它实际上是为了向阿尔玛兹空间站运送船员和货物而设计的
But it was actually designed to deliver crew and cargo to the Almaz space station,
一个秘密的军事空间站
a secret military space station.
尽管整个TKS航天器比阿波罗指挥与服务舱大得多
Despite the entire TKS spacecraft being much larger than the Apollo Command and Service module,
VA航天器本身 可容纳三名宇航员
the VA spacecraft itself that housed up to three cosmonauts
比阿波罗指令舱小30%左右
was about 30% smaller than the Apollo Command Module.
整个TKS航天器的大部分体积来自功能货物舱
Most of the volume of the entire TKS spacecraft came from the Functional Cargo Block
其中有大约37立方米的体积
which had about 37 cubic meters of volume.
现在让我们来对比一下SpaceX的龙飞船 它有10立方米的加压体积
Now let's compare that to SpaceX's Dragon Capsule which has 10 cubic meters of pressurized volume
和14立方米的未加压体积  总共24立方米的体积
and about 14 cubic meters of unpressurized volume, for a total 24 cubic meters of volume.
所以是的 这东西是巨大的
So yeah, this thing was huge.
奇怪的是 第一批8艘VA飞船进行了4次发射
Oddly, the first 8 VA spacecraft flew, on just four flights.
是的 这是非常奇怪的
Yeah that's pretty strange.
从1976年到1979年 VA飞船成对飞行 以在不同的再入条件下进行测试
They would fly them in pairs to test them in varying re-entry conditions flying from 1976 through 1979.
然后 FGB模块和VA飞船一起进行了四次任务 使其成为完整的TKS航天器
Then they even flew four missions with the FGB module and VA capsule making it the complete TKS spacecraft.
尽管四次任务都非常顺利
Despite all four missions going perfectly smooth,
没有人坐过这玩意
no humans ever flew on one.
真是太可惜了
It's really quite a shame.
如果能看到它的运行 那将是一个非常酷的航天器
It would've been a really cool spacecraft to see in operation.
但至少TKS的设计成为了许多空间站部件的基本结构
But at least the TKS design went on to become the basic structure for many space-station parts
包括和平号空间站和国际空间站
including Mir Modules and ISS modules.
最后一个TKS于1991年2月7日离轨再入
The last TKS deorbited on February 7th, 1991
这艘可能是开发最完全的
and was probably one of the most well developed
她是个成功的航天器 但从来没有实现其真正的命运
and successful spacecraft that never get to fulfill its true destiny.
如果你想看到VA舱 你很幸运
If you want to see a VA capsule, you're in luck,
这些东西到处都是
these things are littered everywhere,
包括莫斯科宇航纪念馆
including the Memorial Museum of Cosmonautics in Moscow,
位于华盛顿特区的史密森航空和航天博物馆
The Smithsonian Air and Space Museum in Washington DC,
斯特拉斯堡国际航天大学和其他一些地方
the International Space University in Strasbourg and a few other places.
猎鹰1号
（轻流行音乐）
(light pop music)
我猜大家可能对SpaceX公司的猎鹰9号和重型猎鹰火箭已经非常熟悉了
I'm guessing we're all probably pretty familiar with SpaceX's Falcon 9 and Falcon Heavy rockets by now.
你知道 那些能自己回来降落的火箭
You know, those rockets that land themselves.
对 就是那些
Yeah, those ones.
那么你知道猎鹰9号有一个小弟♂弟吗
Well did you know the Falcon 9 had a baby brother,
或者其实我应该说是一个哥哥
or actually I should probably say an older brother.
猎鹰1号
The Falcon 1.
猎鹰1号是SpaceX从2006年开始制造的第一枚火箭
The Falcon 1 was the first rocket SpaceX built starting in 2006.
它是一枚两级火箭 第一级使用梅林1A或1C发动机
It was a two stage rocket with a Merlin 1A or 1C engine on the first stage
和一个被称为红隼发动机的小型发动机作为上面级发动机
and a little engine known as the Kestrel engine for the upperstage.
SpaceX创始人马一龙从俄罗斯购买火箭的过程中遇到了挫折后 决定研制猎鹰1号
The Falcon 1 came to be when SpaceX founder Elon Musk got frustrated trying to buy a rocket from Russia
他从俄罗斯买火箭是为了向火星发射有效载荷
to launch a small payload to Mars.
他没有成功地做到这一点
He was unsuccessful in doing so.
于是马一龙组建了一个火箭工程师小团队 用自己的钱和一些额外的私人资金
So Elon gathered up a small team of rocket engineers and with his own money and some additional private funds,
马一龙开始证明他可以制造自己的火箭
Elon set off to prove he could build his own rocket,
而且做得比他从俄罗斯买来的还要便宜
and do it even cheaper than he could've bought from Russia.
他和他的团队的目标为制造市场上最便宜的火箭
He and his team set their sights on making the cheapest launcher on the market.
所以在2005年12月 SpaceX公司将他们的第一枚猎鹰1号运到了他们的发射台
So in December 2005 SpaceX rolled their First Falcon 1 out to their launch pad
也就处在太平洋奥梅莱克岛夸贾林环礁的美军基地
at Kwajalein Atoll on a U. S. military base on Omelek Island in the Pacific Ocean.
直到2006年3月 猎鹰1号才首次起飞
It wasn't until March 2006 that the first Falcon 1 took off.
猎鹰1号的前三次飞行都是失败的 有的发射甚至距离入轨只差一步之遥 实在让人沮丧
The first three flights of the Falcon 1 were failures, with some getting frustratingly close to orbit.
事实上 猎鹰1号的第三次飞行几乎就要成功了
As a matter of fact, Falcon 1 flight three would've probably gone off perfectly
如果不是因为第一级的一点残余推力导致两级在分离后立即相撞
if it weren't for a little residual thrust in the first stage causing the stages to collide immediately after separation.
那是因为猎鹰1号在前两次飞行中使用的是梅林1A
That's because the Falcon 1 used the Merlin 1A for the first two flights,
但第三次飞行他们升级为梅林1C
but the third flight they upgraded to the Merlin 1C.
当然 他们(也)测试了梅林1C
Of course they tested the Merlin 1C,
但他们的仪器没有发现发动机关闭后有一点额外的剩余推力
but their instrumentation didn't notice a little extra residual thrust after engine shut off
只有在太空的真空中才会被注意到
that was really only noticeable in the vacuum of space.
所以不幸的是 第一级在阶段分离后 继续加速了一点点
So unfortunately the first stage continued to accelerate just a little bit after stage separation,
使其正好撞上第二级 导致火箭失败
making it run right into the second stage, which unfortunately caused the rocket to fail.
SpaceX公司完蛋了
SpaceX was done for.
他们几乎没有任何现金来建造另一枚猎鹰1号火箭
They had virtually zero cash to build another Falcon 1 rocket,
但他们确实有信心 火箭不需要改变硬件
but they did have confidence that the vehicle required no hardware changes,
只是对软件进行了小小的调整
just a small tweak to the software.
所以马一龙能够在最后时刻获得一些投资
So Elon was able to get a few last minute investments,
刚好够再凑齐一次猎鹰1号的飞行
just enough to scrounge up one more Falcon 1 flight.
随着SpaceX的整个未来都扛在第四枚小小的猎鹰一号肩膀上
With the entire future of SpaceX riding on those tiny metal shoulders of the fourth Falcon 1,
2008年9月28日发射时 大家都屏住了呼吸
breaths were held when it launched on September 28th, 2008.
不过幸运地是 对于SpaceX 当然也包括我们SpaceX的粉丝
But fortunately for SpaceX and of course us SpaceX fans,
猎鹰1号这次发射完美
the Falcon 1 had a flawless mission,
将RatSat质量模拟器送入轨道
putting the RatSat mass simulator into orbit.
这使SpaceX成为第一家入轨的私人公司
This made SpaceX the first privately funded company to reach orbit.
第四次飞行的成功 让SpaceX可以在第五次发射搭载客户的有效载荷
The success of flight four allowed SpaceX to launch a customer's payload for flight five.
于是在2009年7月14日 猎鹰1号第五次也是最后一次起飞
So on July 14, 2009, the Falcon 1 took off for the fifth and final time,
将马来西亚的拉扎克卫星送入轨道
putting the RazakSat into orbit for Malaysia.
还有7次猎鹰1号的发射订单 其中包括猎鹰1号升级版
There were seven additional Falcon 1 flights on the books including upgrades to the Falcon 1,
也就是推力更强 箭体更长的猎鹰1E
which would have made it the Falcon 1E, a more powerful and stretched version.
随着SpaceX公司从NASA中标 要为国际空间站进行补给
With SpaceX winning a bid from NASA for a medium class launcher to supply the International Space Station,
他们决定完全取消猎鹰1号 全力推进猎鹰9号的项目
they decided to cancel the Falcon 1 program entirely and move full steam ahead into their Falcon 9 program.
这样一来 猎鹰1号的7项任务就被推后 最终由猎鹰9号来执行
This left seven missions for the Falcon 1 to be pushed back and eventually flown on Falcon 9s,
或者全部取消
or canceled all together.
这有点让我想起了英国的黑箭计划
This kind of reminds me of the Black Arrow program from the United Kingdom
youtu.be/WcSM7keniZw
我们在第一个视频中谈到过
that we talked about in that first video.
有趣的一点是 猎鹰1号刚投入使用没多久就被取消了
It's kind of funny how the Falcon 1 was canceled as soon as it became operational.
只成功发射过一个客户的有效载荷 然后就关门大吉
Only one customer's payload was ever launched and then closed up shop.
最终看来 SpaceX利用猎鹰1号的成功来铺路 是一个明智之举
It seems like it ended up being a wise move for SpaceX to use the success of their Falcon 1
这就是为了尽快搞出来那个猎鹰9号
to get on over to that Falcon 9 as quickly as possible.
SpaceX的猎鹰1号可能在小卫星这条弯路上走得太远了
SpaceX was probably a bit too far ahead of the small sat curve with the Falcon 1.
视频制作时 猎鹰9号的拼车计划尚未出现
如果他们在小卫星市场大量增加的今天再次研发它 可能会更有意义
Had they developed it today with the massive increase in smallsat market, it would probably be more relevant.
正是现在这个快速增长的市场
This is that same rapidly growing market
让火箭实验室用他们的电子火箭捞了一笔
that Rocket Lab is now successfully fulfilling with their electron rocket.
还有一枚猎鹰1号被制造出来 但从未飞过
There was one more Falcon 1 built but never flown
现在它在霍桑的SpaceX总部的走廊上展出
and is now being displayed in a hallway in SpaceX's Headquarters in Hawthorne.
土星五号
（轻流行音乐）
(light pop music)
最后一个有点不同 因为这枚火箭确实飞得很成功 非常非常成功
Now this last one is a little different because this rocket sure flew, very, very successfully.
事实上 它可能是有史以来最著名的火箭
As a matter of fact, it's probably the most famous rocket of all time,
并完成了令人印象深刻的任务
and fulfilled pretty impressive missions.
我说的当然是带我们登上月球的土星五号火箭
I'm of course talking about the Saturn V rocket that took us to the moon.
那么等等 为什么会出现在这个视频里呢？
So wait, why is it in this video?
嗯 就像我说的 这个只是有点不同
Well, like I said, this one is just a little different,
但这仍然是一个非常有趣的故事
but it's still a really interesting story.
土星五号因飞行13次而闻名
The Saturn V is famous for flying 13 times,
其中12个是完全成功的
12 of them being a complete success,
有9次任务将人类带到月球附近
with nine missions taking humans out to the moon,
其中6次实际着陆月球
six of which actually landed on the moon.
但你知道吗 实际上应该还有另外3次阿波罗登月任务
But did you know, there were actually supposed to be three more Apollo missions to the moon,
而我们已经为这些任务制造了土星五号？
and we had already built the Saturn Vs for those missions?
现在我们不打算在今天的视频中讨论为什么这些阿波罗任务被取消
Now we're not going to get into why these Apollo missions were cancelled in today's video.
这个视频好像也鸽子了，截止20200820没看到
那是另一个关于(架空)航天历史的视频
That's again for another video about alternate space history.
但我们只想说 由于预算的削减和方向的改变 阿波罗18号 19号和20号被取消了
But we'll just say due to budget cuts and changes in direction, Apollo 18, 19 and 20 were canceled.
虽然为月球建造了三枚土星五号
Although three Saturn Vs were built for the moon,
这三者中的一个被用于将 天空实验室送入太空
one of these three got put to use by putting Skylab into space.
但另外两个土星五号留到了现在
But that leaves two other Saturn Vs that are legitimate, flight hardware in existence today.
如果你有机会参观佛罗里达州的肯尼迪航天中心 或者休斯顿的约翰逊航天中心
If you ever get the chance to visit Kennedy Space Center in Florida or Johnson Space Center in Houston,
你会看到真正的土星五号 大部分有着真正的零件 而且是为了登上月球而建造的
you'll see bonafide Saturn Vs that are mostly real flight hardware, built to go to the moon.
在阿拉巴马州 亨茨维尔还有两台全比例的土星五号  一个垂直 一个水平
And there's also two full scale Saturn Vs in Huntsville, Alabama, one vertical and one horizontal.
虽然都不是完整的火箭
And although neither one is full-blown flight hardware,
它们仍然非常非常酷
they're still really, really cool.
但有趣的是 水平的那个是唯一一个完成任务的土星五号
But fun fact, the horizontal one is the only Saturn V on display that completed a mission.
它是用来测试的 通过摇晃来验证土星五号的工程设计
It was the dynamic test vehicle which was shaken to verify the engineering of the Saturn V.
其他完成任务的土星五号都在海底躺着呢
All other Saturn Vs that completed their missions are resting on the bottom of the ocean.
所以虽然这个测试用的土星五号并不会登上月球 但它仍是一个不可思议的展品
So although the Dynamic Test Vehicle wasn't destined for the moon, it's still an incredible display piece.
但这里还有最后一个制造的S1C级 也就是土星五号的第一级
But there's also the last manufactured S1C first stage of a Saturn V
躺在密西西比州无限科学中心的斯坦尼斯航天中心外
sitting outside of Stennis Space Center at the Infinity Science Center in Mississippi.
我想以这个结尾 因为我认为它是苦乐参半的
I wanted to end on this one because I think it's bittersweet.
这里有一些最辉煌的 有史以来最复杂 强大 庞大的工程功绩
Here are some of the most brilliantly complicated, powerful, and massive feats of engineering ever,
具有前所未有的能力 相比于以前或以后的飞行
with more capability than has ever flown before or since,
只是坐在那里 被地球的重力所束缚 尽管他们知道他们有能力将其挣脱
just sitting there, shackled to the Earth by the gravity they know they're capable of breaking free from.
但我也认为这是一种美丽
But I also think it's kind of beautiful.
当然 我真的希望这些东西能飞起来
Sure, I really wish these things could have flown,
再送6个人到月球上
put six more humans on the surface of the moon
参与有史以来历时最长 有最多科学仪器的月球任务
on the longest, most science packed missions we would've ever had.
但与此同时 看看这个
But at the same time, look at this.
现在 任何人都可以亲自去看一下
Now anyone can go see one for themselves.
你可以走在它的下面或旁边
You can walk underneath or alongside it,
花费一两分钟 欣赏所有为这些任务开发的不可思议的硬件
for a minute or two and admire all the incredible hardware developed for these missions.
所以 下次你在计划即将到来的旅行时
So next time you're planning an upcoming trip,
一定要考虑停在休斯顿 亨茨维尔
definitely consider stopping by Houston, Huntsville,
斯坦尼斯航天中心 或者肯尼迪航天中心 欣赏华丽的土星五号
Stennis Space Center, or Kennedy Space Center and admire the gorgeous Saturn V.
每次看到 我还是会无言以对
I still get speechless every single time I see one.
这一切都让你意识到 有一个明确的目标是多么重要
This all just makes you realize how important it is to have a clear goal,
足够的预算和强有力的领导 才能真正做出大的成就
a healthy budget and strong leadership to really make big things happen.
这让我对已经取得的成就感到超级感激
It makes me super thankful for what has been accomplished,
但对本可以做到的感到很沮丧
but also pretty frustrated at what could have been.
youtu.be/WcSM7keniZw
如果你喜欢这段视频 别忘了看看第一集 如果你还没看过
If you enjoyed this video, don't forget to check out part one if you haven't done so already,
我们未来还会出 新的这个系列的视频
but also stick around because we have a lot more coming in this canceled series.
让我知道你还有什么问题
Let me know what other questions you have
关于取消的任务或只是关于航天都在评论区讨论吧
about canceled programs, rockets or just space flight in general in the comments below.
对于我的Patreon支持者 我欠一个大大的感谢 只有他们的帮助 这些视频才有可能做出
I owe a huge thanks to my Patreon supporters for helping make all this stuff possible.
如果你想帮助文案或研究或获得独家现场直播
If you want to help script or research or gain access to excluse live streams
在那里你可以问我关于火箭之类的问题
where you can ask me questions about rockets and stuff,
请前往patreon.com/everydayastronaut
head on over to patreon.com/everydayastronaut.
谢谢你
Thank you.
And while you're online, head on over to my brand new web store where I have things like these.
Grid thin not-a-coasters.
Notice they're not coasters because they have holes in them.
That means the liquid can just drip right through them.
But I do promise they'll keep your drink exactly this high off of water surface they're on
so they're therefore drink elevators.
And while you're there, check out brand new shirts and hats, prints of rocket launches,
patches and stickers, and original artwork.
Lots of fun stuff on my new shop at everydayastronaut.com/shop.
And thanks to you guys I finally got some of my music available anywhere you listen to music.
You can find Maximum Aerodynamic Pressure anywhere.
Apple Music, Google Play Music, Spotify,
Amazon Music, or even a playlist right here on Youtube.
Just search Maximum Aerodynamic Pressure or Everyday Astronaut
and hopefully you'll find it wherever you listen to music.
Give it a listen, enjoy.
谢谢大家
Thanks everybody.
我到这儿就结束了
That does it for me.
我是Tim Dodd 每日宇航员
I'm Tim Dodd, the everyday astronaut
将太空的知识带给地球上的普通人
bringing space down to Earth for everyday people.
（软摇滚音乐）
(soft rock music)
点赞 投币 收藏